Debaa, it is a women dance it is a religious dance of the women
Debaa هو النساء الرقص وهو الدينية رقص النساء
Let's dance for several periods and occasions
دعونا الرقص لعدة فترات ومناسبات
The name of Allah is pronounced
نحن نطق اسم الله
The name of Prophet Mohammed
اسم النبي محمد
and his colleagues, and his parents, his family
وزملائه، والديه وعائلته
and something else
وشيء آخر
We have made several countries
وكان عدد من الدول
at the level of Sufism festivals
المهرجانات مستوى الصوفية
for example in India
على سبيل المثال الهند
In Zanzibar, Copenhagen
زنجبار، كوبنهاغن
in Sweden, Turkey
السويد، تركيا
in London, in Metropolis too
لندن، متروبوليس أيضا
I sing the Debaa since the age of 9
أنا أغني Debaa منذ سن 9 سنوات
at the time the Debaa it was with the men
في الوقت الذي كان Debaa مع الرجال
this is sung by men
هل تغنى بها الرجال
Now they have transmitted to women
النساء الآن فقد تنتقل
and we continued the Debaa until today
واستمر حتى اليوم Debaa
Gestures, it comes in the head We invent
والإيماءات، ويأتي في الرأس واخترع
Search
نحن نبحث
After... When we go to rehearsals
بعد... عندما تذهب إلى البروفات
They tell others. I found a gesture. We'll see if it's pretty.
يقال للآخرين. وجدت لفتة. سنرى ما اذا كان جميلا.
After, everyone, all of us
بعد، الجميع، كل واحد منا
we do it well
هل أحسنت
it is balanced so that is well
هل فعلت لمتوازنة أو جيدا
to make everyone happy and proud
حتى نتمكن جميعا سعداء وفخورون
We pass on to young people we train young people
نحن ينقل إلى الشباب الشباب تشكيل
to take over
لتولي
It's the sweet rhythm
هذا هو إيقاع لطيف
Sufism
الصوفية
between women
بين النساء
This is not a dance of men
انها ليست الرجال الرقص
There are Djinns who love the Debaa
هناك الجن الذين يحبون Debaa
There are Djinns who love Arabic who love Islam
هناك الجن الذين يحبون العربية الذين يحبون الإسلام
Who are Islam itself
من هم حتى الإسلام
and when they hear the Debaa
وعندما يسمعون Debaa
They come to have fun, to dance the Debaa with us
يأتون للحصول على المتعة، الرقص وDebaa معنا
Djinn is a spirit, it's wind it's something like that
الجن هو روح، انها الرياح شيء
In the Quran we say it is people like us
في القرآن ويقال أنه من أناس مثلنا
but we can not see them
ولكن لم يكن احد يرى
He is in the head until death
ومن في رأسه حتى الموت
and when you die it jumps...
وعندما يموت المرء وهو يقفز...
he goes to someone else But he does not die
يذهب إلى شخص آخر لكنه لا يموت
The Djinn does not die
إن الجن لا يموت
There are good and bad
هناك الخير والشر
I would like to tell people
أود أن أقول للناس
What to take in hand our tradition
ما للسيطرة على تقاليدنا
our culture
ثقافة
highlight
معرض
save it
حفظ
and give place
وتعطي مكانه
because a country that has no traditions, culture
لأن البلد ليس لديهم تقاليد والثقافة
This is not good
انها ليست جيدة
It's like someone who has no identity
انها مثل شخص ليس لديه هوية
I say.
أقول.
preserving our culture and traditions
الحفاظ على ثقافتنا وتقاليدنا